Finding Aid for TEACH Michigan and TEACH Michigan Education Fund Records 014 Bj 2
Bentley Historical Library
TEACH Michigan and TEACH Michigan Education Fund records
1989-1996
Bentley Historical Library
TEACH Michigan.
014 Bj 2
13 linear feet
Organization established in 1989 by Paul N. DeWeese and others to lobby for changes in state law and the state constitution to allow parents to choose between competing schools. The record group also contains records of the Michigan Center for Charter Schools, sister organization to TEACH Michigan, established to promote the development of charter schools in the state. The record group includes Informational materials detailing mission and goals of the TEACH Michigan organization; organizational files; topical files; correspondence; speeches and articles about school choice and the state charter school movement; and audio and video cassettes of TM presentations and appearances of Paul DeWeese on radio and television programs. Also included are the organizational records of the Michigan Center for Charter Schools.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The record group came to the library from Partnership for Learning (formerly TEACH Michigan) in December 2000. Donor no. 9038
Conditions Governing Access
Research use of the record group is restricted except with the permission of Dr. Paul DeWeese.
Biographical / Historical
In 1989, Dr. Paul N. DeWeese, a physician then working in Detroit, became frustrated by what he perceived to be a lack of educational choice for his own children then about to begin school. With other like-minded individuals, DeWeese formed Michigan Citizens for Choice in Education (shortly to be renamed TEACH Michigan). Incorporated as a non-profit organization in 1991, TEACH Michigan was established to lobby for changes in the law regarding school choice. Associated with TEACH Michigan was a tax-exempt sister organization - TEACH Michigan Education Fund (TMEF) - which with license to solicit charitable contributions could engage in a variety of educational, research, and planning functions.
Under DeWeese's leadership, TEACH Michigan advocated fundamental changes in the state's educational system. The core of TEACH Michigan's philosophy of education was simply stated. Parents should be allowed to choose from competing systems of schools with funding for education following the student and not automatically being given to the government-supported school system. An ambitious agenda, TEACH Michigan realized the importance of educating the public and enlisting enough grassroots support for the necessary changes in state law and in the state constitution to be made. With the law changed, there would follow competition for the education dollar resulting in non-governmental sponsorship of K-12 schools by corporations, public or private universities, parent groups or churches, as well as by the government. No longer would there be a "government monopoly" school system. Instead, parents would receive financial support (or vouchers) for their children to attend the school of their choice.
Although his message never wavered, DeWeese was realistic enough to realize that "full choice" could only come incrementally, thus his advocacy of changes in state law to allow for the creation of charter schools. Charter schools are public schools that are custom-designed by groups of teachers, parents or outside individuals to meet particular education needs. Charter schools are part of the public school system, financed on a par with other schools in the district. But for charter schools to become a reality state law would have to be changed. In December 1993, with the passage of Senate bill no. 896 (signed by the governor in January 1994), Michigan adopted the most significant restructuring of public education since the development of single-function school districts in the early 20th century. The state authorized groups of certified teachers and community leaders to form individual charter schools (public school academies) "that are to be treated like school districts" for the purposes of state education law. These "single-school school districts" could be started anywhere in the state by one or more certified teachers, a county, city, village, township, school district, community college, or state public university. Each new school would develop its own governing board, and must describe its educational goals and the standards by which its performance will be measured. Each of these academies would receive a state school aid payment for its enrolled students.
Following the passage of 896, TMEF established a sister organization, the Michigan Center for Charter Schools (MCCS), whose purpose was to promote the development of charter schools. TMEF subsidized the operation of MCCS throughout its existence. MCCS was the only organization in the state early on that was disseminating timely and accurate information about charter schools. MCCS also helped several groups move through the process of establishing a charter school. By the end of 1995, more than 60 charter school had been established with an additional 120 schools seeking charters.
In November 1994, an Ingham County circuit court judge ruled the law unconstitutional. Although the groups authorized to grant charters were government entities, the judge ruled, the day-to-day operations of schools were largely in the hands of privately elected directors and thus not directly accountable to the public. With this decision, the charter schools that had been established were left without public funding. In some cases, the schools reverted to private school status relying on tuitions and corporate donations for their support. In other cases, the state legislature, many of whose members believed that the judge's ruling would be overturned on appeal, passed emergency legislation which addressed the judge's objection to the original legislation.
In 1995, the state Board of Education contracted with the Michigan Partnership for New Education to both promote charter schools and to provide technical assistance to charter schools. The Michigan Partnership immediately asked for, and received, permission to hire the entire staff of MCCS in order to run their charter school operation. In May of 1995, MCCS ceased to operate, as its mission and staff were absorbed by the Michigan Partnership for New Education.
From its inception, TEACH Michigan knew that for real educational reform to take place from their point of view, the Michigan State Constitution (Article 8, sec. 2) would have to be revised. That provision restricted the use of public funds to government-operated schools only. With the constitution changed, TEACH Michigan hoped to secure passage of a voucher system so that parents might choose, and receive funding, for their child to attend a church-related school.
In 2000, the TEACH Michigan organization was folded into a new organization, Partnership for Learning.
Scope and Contents
This record group consists of two separate groupings (or subgroups) of records: the combined files of TEACH Michigan and TEACH Michigan Education Fund covering the period of 1989 to 1995, and files of the charter school support group, Michigan Center for Charter Schools covering the years 1994-1995. Both organizations operated out of the same office in Lansing and included some of the same individuals as board members. The TM/TMEF files consist in great part of papers of Dr. Paul N. DeWeese, a principal founder of the organization. The MCCS files are largely papers of executive director Barbara Barrett as well as DeWeese. Together, the record group contains correspondence, policy statements, organizational and activity files, collected materials, sound and video materials, all relating to the efforts of the two organizations first to educate and lobby for changes in the law, and second to provide assistance and support in the establishment of charter schools. The records date from the inception of the organization to 1995. The subsequent records of TEACH Michigan remain with the organization.
Charter schools -- Michigan.; Education -- Michigan.; Public schools -- Michigan.; School choice -- Michigan.; Charter schools -- Michigan.; Debates.; Discussion.; Public affairs television programs.; School choice -- Michigan.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.; DeWeese, Paul N.; Michigan Center for Charter Schools.; TEACH Michigan.; TEACH Michigan Education Fund.; DeWeese, Paul N.; TEACH Michigan.; DeWeese, Paul N.; Michigan Center for Charter Schools.; TEACH Michigan Education Fund.
- TEACH Michigan/Teach Michigan Education Fund
  Scope and Contents
  The TEACH Michigan/Teach Michigan Education Fund subgroup consists of the following series: Informational Files; Organizational Materials; Topical Files; Correspondence; Speeches and Articles; and Audio-Visual Materials.
  - Informational Files
    The Informational files series within TM/TMED is noteworthy for the educational journal/log maintained by DeWeese during the early period when he was establishing the TM choice organization. Also included here are the various statements and brochures put out by the organization to explain its mission and its goals.
    - Journal of TM activities maintained by Paul DeWeese, 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - Paul DeWeese biographical information (Box 1)
    - Informational packet about TMEF (Box 1)
    - Brochures, informational statements, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Organizational Materials
    The Organizational Materials series includes files relating to the operation and administration of TM/TMEF. Included are files from various meetings, reports, and newsletters.
    - Michigan Citizens for Choice in Education
      - Name change, 1990 (Box 1)
      - Task force meeting and list of task force members, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, articles of incorporation, communications with law firm regarding IRS status (Box 1)
    - TEACH Michigan reorganization memorandum, October 1993 (Box 1)
    - Meetings
      - TMEF board of directors meetings (agenda and minutes), 1991 (Box 1)
      - Ad hoc Committee, 1990 (Box 1)
      - Strategic Planning Meetings (kitchen cabinet), 1993; 1995 (Box 1)
      - Coalition (Coalition for Better Schools) meetings, 1993; 8 folders (Box 1)
      - Private School Input session, 1993 (Box 1)
      - Steering Committee, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Various reports and plans
      - Chairman's Report, 1993 (Box 1)
      - Executive Memorandum: "As I See It", 1991 (Box 1)
      - Communication Plan for TMEF (prepared by Tom Berriman), 1993 (Box 1)
      - TEACH Plan (Box 1)
      - Teachers for Choice proposal (Box 1)
      - Vision statement (Box 1)
      - Various (Box 1)
    - Newsletters (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1993-1994; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Contact List (Box 1)
    - Corporate leaders (list of) (Box 1)
    - Memorandum regarding working relations between TMEF and Michigan Center for Charter Schools, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Topical File
    The Topical File series is the largest grouping of files. Partially drawn together various files of DeWeese and others, this series contains the most complete documentation of TM/TMED activities. In this series will be found files relating to organizational strategy and planning, with substantive material on constitutional reform and the organization's support for specific pieces of legislation. Also noteworthy in this series are files relating to the relationship between TM and other related organizations, such as the Michigan Association of Non-Public Schools (MANS), the Coalition for Better Schools, and the Mackinac Center for Public Policy.
    - African American issues (Clinton Canady III) (Box 1)
    - "At Risk" Children White Paper (Box 1)
    - Bradley Foundation request (Box 1)
    - Catholic Campaign for America (Box 1)
    - Chapter materials
      - Chapter kit (Box 1)
      - Chapter lists (Box 1)
      - Chapter manuals (Box 1)
      - Leadership Training Seminar, November 7, 1992 (Box 1)
      - Memoranda of Renee Oliver, administrative assistant, chapter formation (Box 1)
    - Charter school notes (Box 1)
    - Chrysler Corp. (Box 1)
      General
      request for grant regarding parent empowerment
    - Coalition for Better Schools (Box 2)
    - Communitarian Network (Box 2)
    - Conferences, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Constitutional amendment (revision research), 9 folders (Box 2)
    - Consultants
      - Berg, Bob (Box 2)
      - Market Research Group (Box 2)
      - Public Sector Consultants (Box 2)
      - Vanden Berg, Mark (Box 2)
    - Detroit Archdiocese (Box 2)
    - Detroit schools (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - Financial (statements, budgets, etc.), 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Fundraising events and mailings, 12 folders (Box 3)
    - Herrick Foundation proposal, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Keller Foundation (Box 3)
    - Legal Strategy Planning Group, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Legislation
      - Public Act 118 (Box 3)
      - Public Act 362 (Senate Bill 896), 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Senate Bill 887 (Box 3)
      - Senate Bill 1103 (Box 3)
      - House Bill 4365 (Box 3)
      - House Bill 5463 (Box 3)
      - Charter school legislation (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
      - School code reform (Box 3)
    - Legislators
      - DeGrow, Daniel (Box 3)
      - Welborn, Jack (Box 3)
      - Legislative candidates questionnaire, 1994 (Box 3)
      - Legislators (general) (Box 3)
    - Litigation
      - Legal defense against Michigan Education Association (Box 3)
      - Noah Webster Academy suit, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Mackinac Center for Public Policy public school choice study, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Michigan Association of Christian Schools (Box 3)
    - Michigan Association of Non-Public Schools
      - Board meetings, 1992-1994; 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Action Plan (Box 3)
      - Contacts (Box 3)
      - Issues raised at regional meetings (Box 3)
      - Regional meetings (Box 3)
      - School presentation (Box 3)
      - Toward Educational Choice (joint meeting with TEACH Michigan) (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Michigan Bankers Association (Box 3)
    - Michigan Catholic Conference (Box 3)
    - Michigan Center for Charter Schools (general) (Box 3)
    - Michigan Educational Association/National Education Association (Box 3)
    - Michigan Family Forum (Box 4)
    - Michigan Future (Doug Ross) (Box 4)
    - Michigan Manufacturers Association (Box 4)
    - Michigan Merchants Council (Box 4)
    - Michigan Partnership for New Education (Box 4)
    - Michigan Property Owners Association (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Neola, Inc. proposal (Box 4)
    - People of color issues (Box 4)
    - Polling surveys and studies, 0.67 linear feet (Box 4)
      unprocessed
    - Press Secretary (Jena Jenson files), 0.33 linear feet (Box 4)
    - Research (general) (Box 5)
    - Retreats, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Right to Life of Michigan (Box 5)
    - School choice (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - School to Work programs (Box 5)
    - Speakers' Bureau, 7 folders (Box 5)
    - Strategic planning and research, 0.67 linear feet (Box 5)
      includes Bannon Associates Strategic Plan materials
    - Talent agents (Box 5)
    - Teacher Coordinator (Box 5)
    - Teacher involvement (Box 5)
    - Teachers choice program (Michigan Network of Empowered Teachers) (Box 5)
    - Urban strategy (Box 5)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence series dates from 1989 to 1995 and consists of copies of outgoing correspondence from DeWeese and others. There is relatively little incoming correspondence. The letters are valuable in content though somewhat repetitive in that the same message was going to different individuals or organizations.
    - Office Correspondence (mainly Paul DeWeese)
      - December 1989-December 1992 (Box 6)
      - 1993-1995 (Box 7)
    - DeWeese Correspondence
      - 1991-July 1994 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Mass mailings (Box 8)
      - Faxes (Box 8)
      - Various staff (Box 8)
  - Speeches and Articles
    The Speeches and Articles series consists of the many messages, articles, and op-ed newspaper pieces written or delivered by DeWeese and other TM supporters on the topic of educational choice, charter schools, and related topics.
    - Speeches by Paul DeWeese
      - Undated, 1991-1995 (Box 9)
    - Speeches by others
      - Various talks by TEACH Michigan associates (Box 9)
    - Articles written by DeWeese
      - Statements written for TEACH Michigan and for op-ed pages of newspapers (Box 9)
    - Articles written by others
      - Various articles by TEACH Michigan associates, etc (Box 9)
  - Audio-Visual Materials
    The Audio-Visual Materials series contains both audio and visual cassette tapes of TM presentations, debates, or appearances by DeWeese on radio or television programs.
    - Audio cassettes and videocassettes of speeches, programs, etc. (Box 10)
      not further described
- Michigan Center for Charter Schools
  The second subgroup within this record group are files of the Michigan Center for Charter Schools during the period of its organizational life, 1994 to 1995. The organization was established to provide support and encouragement to charter schools in Michigan, thus there is much documentation on the actual process of establishing such a school. The MCCS subgroup consists of the following series: Foundations/Funding Corporations; Topical Files; Conferences and Forums; Correspondence; Record Books; Charter Schools - Governing entities; Charter Schools (by name); and Statements, Guidelines, etc.
  - Foundations/Funding Corporations
    - Amway Corp (Box 11)
    - Annenberg Foundation (Box 11)
    - Chrysler Corp (Box 11)
    - City Management Corp (Box 11)
    - Detroit Center Tool, Inc (Box 11)
    - Detroit Edison (Box 11)
    - Detroit Renaissance (Box 11)
    - DeVos Proposal (Box 11)
    - Donnelly Corp (Box 11)
    - Dow Chemical (Box 11)
    - DPCS International (Box 11)
    - First of America (Box 11)
    - Ford Motor Co (Box 11)
    - Herrick Foundation (Box 11)
    - Inacom Corp (Box 11)
    - Kellogg Foundation, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - McGregor Fund (Box 11)
    - Meijer Proposal (Box 11)
    - MichCon Foundation (Box 11)
    - Old Kent Bank (Box 11)
    - Smith Richardson Foundation (Box 11)
    - Spartan Motors Proposal (Box 11)
    - West Michigan Equities (Box 11)
    - Whirlpool Corporation (Box 11)
    - World Heritage Foundation (Box 11)
  - Topical Files
    - Academic Freedom Amendments (Box 11)
    - Advisory Board (Box 11)
    - Agreements (Box 11)
    - Allen, William B (Box 11)
    - Amendments (Box 11)
    - Articles of Incorporation (Box 11)
    - Articles (newspapers, etc.), 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Biography (Box 11)
    - Board of Directors (Box 11)
    - Budget (Box 11)
    - Bylaws (Box 11)
    - Charter School Law and Revision (Box 11)
    - Charter Schools (Box 11)
    - Contracts (Box 11)
    - DeWeese, Paul (Box 11)
    - Dissolution (Agenda for final board meeting) (Box 11)
    - Dykema Gossett (Box 11)
    - Events-Media (Box 11)
    - Governor's Conference on Charter Schools (Box 11)
    - Informational materials (Box 11)
    - Mallison, David (Box 11)
    - Michigan Forward (Box 11)
    - Michigan Partnership for New Education (Box 11)
    - Michigan Public School Academy Service Corp. (Box 11)
    - Minutes, 6 folders (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - Press Information (Box 11)
    - Press Releases (Box 11)
    - Public Education Charter (Box 11)
    - Responsibilities (Box 11)
    - Staff meetings (Box 11)
    - Vitullo-Martin, Tom (Box 11)
    - Wittman, Bob (Box 11)
  - Conferences and forums
    - 1994-1995, 15 folders (Box 12)
  - Correspondence
    - 1994-1995, 7 folders (Box 12)
      includes one folder of faxes
  - Record books
    - Model Charter School Documentation (Box 12)
    - Model Documents for Establishing a Charter Public School in Michigan (Box 12)
    - Corporate record book (Box 12)
      includes articles, bylaws, legal documents
    - Binder containing various documentation (Box 12)
      include planning documents, committees, law, articles and bylaws
  - Charter Schools-Governing entities
    - Central Michigan University (Box 13)
    - Neola of Michigan (Box 13)
    - Northern Michigan University (Box 13)
    - People's Community Baptist Church (Box 13)
    - Saginaw Valley State University (Box 13)
  - Charter Schools (by name)
    - Casa Maria Academy (Box 13)
    - Crescent Academy International (Box 13)
    - Detroit Academy of Arts and Sciences (Box 13)
    - Detroit Inter-faith Pastors (Box 13)
    - Early Childhood Charter School (Box 13)
    - Edison Project (Box 13)
    - Island City Academy (Box 13)
    - Macomb Christian Schools (Box 13)
    - Mid-Michigan Academy (Box 13)
    - Montessori Children's House (Box 13)
    - New Branches Charter School (Box 13)
    - Noah Webster Academy (Box 13)
    - Northlane Day School (Box 13)
    - Northside Preparatory School (Box 13)
    - Plymouth Day School (Box 13)
    - Rainbow Youth Academy (Box 13)
    - Sankofa Shule (Box 13)
    - Technical Manufacturing Academy (Box 13)
    - Thomas Gist Academy, 1 folders; 1 Volumes (Box 13)
    - West Michigan Service Academy (Box 13)
    - West Michigan Academy for Hospitality Sciences (Box 13)
  - Statements, guidelines, etc
    - Accomplishments to date (Box 13)
    - Agenda for starting (Box 13)
    - Authorizer's Review of Charter School Plan (Box 13)
    - Bullet Points regarding Charter Schools (Box 13)
    - Charter School growth (MI) (Box 13)
    - Community Outreach Activities (Box 13)
    - Conflict of Interest (Box 13)
    - Critical Orbit (Box 13)
    - Current Status of Law (Box 13)
    - Development Stages (Box 13)
    - Development Timetable (Box 13)
    - Diversity Report (Box 13)
    - Diversity Tables (Box 13)
    - Estimated Annual Increase (Box 13)
    - Estimated Rate of Formation (Box 13)
    - Fact Sheet (Box 13)
    - Federal/State Grant Monies (Box 13)
    - Fiscal Agency Agreement (Box 13)
    - Growth in Three Years (Box 13)
    - Key Principles (Box 13)
    - Keys for Developing and Operating a Successful Charter School (Box 13)
    - List of Schools (Box 13)
    - Mission Statement (Box 13)
    - National/International Perspective (Box 13)
    - Overview (Box 13)
    - Plan, 1994 (Box 13)
    - Planning Process Summary (Box 13)
    - Profile (MCCS) (Box 13)
    - Profiles (Box 13)
    - Project Management (Box 13)
    - Project Management Tracking (Box 13)
    - Proposal (MCCS) (Box 13)
    - Prospects for Support (Box 13)
    - Publications List (Box 13)
    - School-to-work (Box 13)
    - Status of charter schools (Box 13)
    - Synopsis of Center (Box 13)
    - Technical Assistance Services (Box 13)
    - Three Year Budget (Box 13)
    - Timeplan (proposed) (Box 13)
    - Trust Fund case statement (Box 13)
    - Understanding Michigan Charter School Law (Box 13)
    - Update on Michigan's Charter School Legislation (Box 13)